Preliminary Guide to the South Atlantic Quarterly Records, 1926 - 1986
University Archives Duke University
South Atlantic Quarterly records 1926 - 1986
Duke University Press.
25.0 Linear Feet, 25000 Items
University Archives, Duke University
The South Atlantic Quarterly was founded in 1901 at Trinity College (later Duke University), and faculty from Trinity College and Duke University have served on its editorial board since its inception. The periodical, published by Duke University Press since 1930, began as a scholarly and literary journal about southern topics, and has since expanded to discuss national and international issues. The South Atlantic Quarterly Records consist mainly of correspondence regarding manuscript submissions and editing issues. Other materials include Board of Directors minutes, subject files, and content lists for individual issues of South Atlantic Quarterly.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
Unprocessed materials are closed pending processing.
In off-site storage; 48 hours advance notice is required for use.
Provenance
The South Atlantic Quarterly Records were received by the University Archives as a deposit in 1958, 1973, 1981, 1982, 1985, and 1991.
Historical Note
The South Atlantic Quarterly was founded in 1901 by John Spencer Bassett, a professor of English at Trinity College (later Duke University). Funded by Trinity College faculty and administrators, as well as by philanthropists, the scholarly and literary journal was devoted to discussing and critiquing southern topics. The first issue was published in January 1902. Bassett published an essay in the October 1903 issue that was critical of racist political tactics and drew national attention to Trinity College and the issue of academic freedom.
In approximately 1908, Trinity College, and later Duke University, began to support the journal financially. The South Atlantic Quarterly has been published by the Duke University Press. The journal has been continually published with a volunteer editorial staff. Faculty members from the Departments of English and History have served as the journal's editor. Over time, the journal's focus has expanded to include not only southern topics but also those of national and international interest.
Collection Overview
The South Atlantic Quarterly Records consist mainly of correspondence regarding manuscript submissions and editing issues. Other materials include Board of Directors minutes, subject files, and content lists for individual issues of South Atlantic Quarterly. The materials date from the mid-1920s to the mid-1980s. The collection is organized according to accession number, from earliest to latest.
Subject Headings
These and related materials may be accessed under the following subject headings in the Duke University Libraries online catalog.
American literature -- 20th century
Duke University -- Faculty
Duke University -- History
Duke University Press
Southern States -- Social conditions -- Periodicals
United States -- Social conditions -- Periodicals
South Atlantic quarterly
Contents of Collection
- Container List
  The South Atlantic Quarterly Records are only preliminarily processed. The lists of materials within each box represent major subjects, but they are not folder lists.
  - Accession #A59-69, 1932-1957
    - Correspondence, A-Jo (Box 1)
      This correspondence is regarding manuscript submissions and editing issues. It is organized alphabetically by correspondent name.
    - Correspondence, Jo-Wa (Box 2)
    - Correspondence, We-Y (Box 3)
    - Files on various types of writings, i.e. fiction, poems, book reviews
    - Reprint Permissions
    - Press Prize Award
    - Duke Press Info
    - Board of Directors Minutes
    - Frank C. Brown correspondence
    - Yearly correspondence
    - Manuscripts and correspondence about accepted manuscripts (Box 4)
  - Accession #73-148, 1926
    - William Kenneth Boyd correspondence
  - Accession #81-32, 1933-1968
    This series contains correspondence regarding manuscript submissions and editing issues. It is organized alphabetically by correspondent name.
    - Correspondence, A-Gi (Box 5)
    - Correspondence, Go-Mo (Box 6)
    - Correspondence, Mu-Z (Box 7)
  - Accession #82-26, 1935-1979
    This series contains correspondence regarding manuscript submissions. It is organized alphabetically by correspondent name.
    - Correspondence, A-Br (Box 8)
    - Correspondence, Br-Do (Box 9)
    - Correspondence, Dr-Gr (Box 10)
    - Correspondence, H-Ke (Box 11)
    - Correspondence, Ke-Me (Box 12)
    - Correspondence, Me-Pi (Box 13)
    - Correspondence, Pi-Sh (Box 14)
    - Correspondence, Sh-Ty (Box 15)
    - Correspondence, U-Z (Box 16)
  - Accession #85-40, 1982-1983
    - "Foul" Manuscripts, 1982-1983 (Box 17)
  - Accession #91-121, 1955-1986
    - Correspondence (Box 18)
    - List of contents of South Atlantic Quarterly, 1969-1986
Related Material
Bassett (John S.) Collection, 1802-1998
Duke University Archives
Bassett Affair Collection, 1903-2003
Duke University Archives
Watson (Richard L) Papers, 1941-1989
Duke University Archives
Bibliography
William Baskerville Hamilton, Fifty Years of the South Atlantic Quarterly, Durham, N.C.: Duke University Press, 1952